Thank you very much. Oh dear. Oh dear. Now what?
Hartelijk dank. Oh lieverd. Oh lieverd. Wat nu?
>> We're going to be doing a little bit of dialoguing um this afternoon. Can you
>> We gaan een beetje doen vanmiddag een dialoog aangegaan. Kun jij
hear me? Okay. Oh, there we are. Um and we're going to be talking about living
hoor mij? Oké. O, daar zijn we dan. Eh en we gaan het hebben over leven
in the present and how you go about living in the present. Uh not in the
in het heden en hoe je omgaat leven in het heden. Eh niet in de
future, not in the past, but living with what's happening right now in your life.
toekomst, niet in het verleden, maar ermee leven wat er nu gebeurt in je leven.
So, we're going to be doing a little bit of dialoguing on that.
We gaan dus een beetje aan de slag daarover in dialoog te gaan.
>> Well, people liked the dialoguing we did before, so we thought we'd
>> Nou, mensen vonden de dialoog die we voerden leuk eerder, dus we dachten van wel
>> try >> repeat it and see if they still like it.
>> proberen >> herhaal het en kijk of ze het nog steeds leuk vinden.
And if not, if not, we'll fold up our tent and
En zo niet, zo niet, dan vouwen we onze tent op en
silently slink away. >> Okay. So how does one um
stilletjes wegsluipen. >> Oké. Dus hoe gaat een eh
how does one let go of the past? How do you let go of past um say
hoe laat je het verleden los? Hoe laat je het verleden los, zeg maar
oh the effects of the past? How do you let go of the effects that the past has
oh de gevolgen van het verleden? Hoe gaat het? Laat de gevolgen van het verleden los
had on one's life? >> Well, you look at it as instant karma.
gehad op iemands leven? >> Nou, je beschouwt het als onmiddellijk karma.
You just goofed up. Now you suffer. Huh? So why protest the suffering that
Je hebt gewoon gek gedaan. Nu heb je last. Hè? Dus waarom protesteren tegen het lijden dat
yourself created? Of course, you always blame it on somebody else,
zelf gemaakt? Natuurlijk, jij altijd geef de schuld aan iemand anders,
>> right? >> You know,
>> toch? >> Weet je,
>> you have a tendency to always say, well, if you hadn't done that, I I wouldn't
>> je hebt de neiging om altijd te zeggen, nou, Als je dat niet had gedaan, zou ik het niet doen
have happened to me. >> That's true. Yeah. You want to get rid
zijn mij overkomen. >> Dat is waar. Ja. Je wilt er vanaf
of the the responsibility, >> right?
van de verantwoordelijkheid, >> toch?
>> Yeah. And the only the only way I I've
>> Ja. En de enige manier waarop ik dat heb gedaan
discovered is is uh is for the mind to become silent.
ontdekt is dat het voor de geest is om dat te doen stil worden.
And when the mind is silent, uh that answers the whole problem.
En als de geest stil is, uh, dat lost het hele probleem op.
>> Okay. How do you make the mind silent? >> Because we keep running this whole
>> Oké. Hoe maak je de geest stil? >> Omdat we dit geheel blijven runnen
picture, you know, it keeps going on. This whole picture in the back of your
foto, weet je, het blijft maar doorgaan. Deze hele foto achterin je
mind keeps happening. So how do you make the mind go? Well, like you said, the
de geest blijft gebeuren. Dus hoe maak je de geest gaan? Nou, zoals je zei, de
picture is either of the anticipation of the future. The mind never loses in the
foto is een van de verwachtingen van de toekomst. De geest verliest nooit in de
present. In order to survive, it has to
cadeau. Om te overleven moet het wel
anticipate the future and it has to regret the past. So, if you refuse those
anticiperen op de toekomst en dat moet ook spijt van het verleden. Dus als je die weigert
payoffs, so those are payoffs. And uh in order to propagate itself,
uitbetalingen, dus dat zijn uitbetalingen. En om zichzelf te verspreiden,
what the ego hates is having nothing to do because then it's afraid it will no
wat het ego haat, is dat je niets te doen hebt doen omdat het dan bang is dat het niet zal gebeuren
longer exist. So it keeps itself busy dreaming up
langer bestaan. Het houdt zichzelf dus bezig met dromen
problems for the future and inventing regrets over the past. Of course,
problemen voor de toekomst en uitvinden heeft spijt van het verleden. Natuurlijk,
neither one of them has any reality and therefore you stay in a state of
geen van beiden heeft enige realiteit en daarom blijf je in een staat van
non-reality. The only way to let let have it all stop
niet-realiteit. De enige manier om het allemaal te laten stoppen
is to let go the desire to think, which means letting go the pay payoff of
is het verlangen om te denken los te laten betekent het loslaten van de uitbetaling van
thinkingness. And the mind says, well, if you don't
denkvermogen. En de geest zegt: als je dat niet doet
think and plan, you won't survive. So, you they really have to in a way give up
denk en plan, je overleeft het niet. Dus, jij, ze moeten het in zekere zin echt opgeven
the will to survive. And you either survive or you don't. And
de wil om te overleven. En je overleeft het of je overleeft het niet. En
uh that's God's problem. Well, God created you, didn't he? So,
Euh, dat is Gods probleem. Nou, God heeft jou geschapen, nietwaar? Dus,
all right. So, you got to take responsibility.
oké. Dus je moet nemen verantwoordelijkheid.
>> So, you have to remind him once in a while. I don't remember asking to be
>> Je moet hem er dus af en toe aan herinneren terwijl. Ik kan me niet herinneren dat ik dat heb gevraagd
created, you know. It was your idea. You know what I mean?
gecreëerd, weet je. Het was jouw idee. Weet je wat ik bedoel?
>> Okay. >> Well, it wasn't my idea.
>> Oké. >> Nou, het was niet mijn idee.
>> To create a world. >> That sounds a little too ambitious for
>> Om een ​​wereld te creëren. >> Dat klinkt iets te ambitieus
me. If I can get from here to there, I think
mij. Als ik van hier naar daar kan komen, denk ik
it's a good day. So when your mind keeps replaying say a
het is een goede dag. Dus als je geest blijft herhalen, zeg dan a
um a tragic event that happened in your life the replay
Uh, een tragische gebeurtenis die in uw land heeft plaatsgevonden leven de herhaling
>> so you know your mind has a tendency to want to replay that.
>> zodat je weet dat je geest daartoe geneigd is wil dat opnieuw afspelen.
>> So we're getting juice out of that replays it.
>> Dus daar halen we sap uit herhaalt het.
>> So it's really the willingness to give up the juice.
>> Het is dus eigenlijk de bereidheid om te geven het sap op.
>> The payoff is the juice. >> Okay.
>> De uitbetaling is het sap. >> Oké.
>> And that's the only fuel that the ego has is juice.
>> En dat is de enige brandstof die het ego voedt heeft is sap.
So when you deprive it of juice by being willing to let it go uh and and then
Dus als je het van sap berooft door te zijn bereid om het los te laten, uh en en dan
then the mind's faculties become juiceless and when it's juiceless it
dan worden de vermogens van de geest saploos en als het saploos is
stops it abandons everything and you live in silence. uh the inner
stopt, het laat alles achter en je leeft in stilte. eh de binnenkant
mind is silent and uh so you stop identifying with the
de geest is stil en uh, dus je identificeert je niet meer met de
talkingness and you see you become the witness so
spraakzaamheid en je ziet dat je zo de getuige wordt
I'll say you stop participating in the participating in the dialogue you become
Ik zeg dat je stopt met meedoen aan de deelnemen aan de dialoog die je wordt
the witness of the dialogue I mean who's complaining about the past or the
de getuige van de dialoog, ik bedoel wie is klagen over het verleden of de
present u who is it that's complaining
aanwezig u wie is het die klaagt
you well and how do you know what's going on to let go identifying with the
het gaat goed met je en hoe weet je wat er is Ik ga door met het loslaten van de identificatie met de
dialogue and let go identifying with the mind and become the witness of the mind.
dialoog en laat de identificatie met de geest en word de getuige van de geest.
So you back off from identifying with all the chitchat
Dus je vermijdt je te identificeren met al dat geklets
>> and you realize how do I know what this how how do I even know there's chitchat
>> en je realiseert je hoe weet ik wat dit is Hoe weet ik dat er gepraat wordt?
going on? It's because of the observer. So I always say the way out of the ego
aan de hand? Het komt door de waarnemer. Dus ik zeg altijd: de uitweg uit het ego
is to back out through the witness observer witness-observer.
is om terug te komen via de getuige waarnemer getuige-waarnemer.
Uh because that's not difficult to do. You be you can begin to realize that
Uh, want dat is niet moeilijk om te doen. Je kunt je dat gaan realiseren
which I am is the witness, the observer and not the participant. Because how do
die ik ben is de getuige, de waarnemer en niet de deelnemer. Want hoe doe je dat?
you know you're a participant? Because you witness it and observe it. So back
Weet je dat je deelnemer bent? Omdat je bent er getuige van en observeert het. Dus terug
into identifying with uh the witness observer and then you
om zich mee te identificeren uh de getuige-waarnemer en dan jij
then you go from witness observer to how do you know what is being witnessed and
dan ga je van getuige-waarnemer naar hoe weet je wat er wordt gezien en
observed and then you back up into awareness
waargenomen en dan kom je weer in bewustzijn
itself? The only thing you're aware of is
zelf? Het enige waar jij je van bewust bent is
awareness. That's all you're aware of is awareness itself.
bewustzijn. Dat is het enige waar u zich van bewust bent bewustzijn zelf.
You know, the awareness of what is irrelevant because there's always
Je weet wel, het bewustzijn van wat is niet relevant, want dat is er altijd
something you can be aware of. I remember that cartoon
iets waar je je bewust van kunt zijn. Ik herinner me die tekenfilm
from many years ago. I think it was a Fleer's gum cartoon. Fleer's gum came
van vele jaren geleden. Ik denk dat het een Fleer's kauwgom cartoon. Fleer's kauwgom kwam
with a cartoon on the rapper and and it shows this kid and he's sitting on the
met een cartoon over de rapper en en het laat deze jongen zien en hij zit op de
curb and he's got a Fleer's gum wrapper. He's so bored that he's reading the
stoeprand en hij heeft een kauwgomverpakking van Fleer. Hij verveelt zich zo dat hij de tekst leest
rapper and he's reading all the ingredients in this
rapper en hij leest alle ingrediënten hierin
the gum, you know, reading, you know, so he's reading all the
de kauwgom, je weet wel, lezen, Weet je, dus hij leest alles
ingredients in this gum, you know, because he's so bored. He doesn't he
ingrediënten in deze kauwgom, weet je, omdat hij zich zo verveelt. Dat doet hij niet
wants he's got to keep his mind busy. So even a fleer's gum wrapper is
wil dat hij zijn gedachten bezig moet houden. Dus zelfs een kauwgomverpakking is dat wel
interesting when you're frantically bored.
interessant als je in paniek raakt verveeld.
So, so when your mind starts to replay this tragedy and you start to s feel
Dus, dus wanneer je geest begint te herhalen deze tragedie en je begint het te voelen
sorry for what has happened, then what you what you're saying is that you
Sorry voor wat er is gebeurd, en dan jij, wat je zegt, is dat jij
should let it run its course or or try and stop it before it starts. Well, once
moet het zijn beloop laten of proberen en stop het voordat het begint. Nou ja, een keer
you become aware that what the ego is doing is constantly juicing things,
je wordt je bewust van wat het ego is doen is voortdurend dingen uitpersen,
juicing subjects, it's juicing the past and regret over the past and it's
onderwerpen uitpersen, het verleden uitpersen en spijt van het verleden en dat is zo
juicing the future. Uh just like it it loves controversy
de toekomst verpesten. Uh, net zo houdt het van controverse
>> because controversy is full of uh ego juice.
>> omdat controverse vol zit met ego sap.
And uh when if you're really interested in in becoming enlightened, then it
En eh, als je echt geïnteresseerd bent in het verlicht worden, dan is het dat
means to let go uh the mind. itself. Let go all conceptual thought.
betekent het loslaten van de geest. zelf. Laat ga helemaal conceptueel denken.
Stop talking about phenomena. Stop u
Stop met praten over verschijnselen. Houd u tegen
wording it, picturing it. And you become you you you back up into
door het te verwoorden, het in beeld te brengen. En jij wordt jij jij jij waar je een back-up van maakt
the self as a silent presence. Silent presence of what? Silence presence of
het zelf als een stille aanwezigheid. Stil aanwezigheid van wat? Stilte aanwezigheid van
the observer witness aspect of consciousness itself. Eventually you
het waarnemer-getuige-aspect van bewustzijn zelf. Uiteindelijk jij
realize that that that which is consciousness, that which is the self
besef dat dat wat is bewustzijn, dat wat het zelf is
with a capital S are one and the same thing.
met een hoofdletter S zijn één en hetzelfde ding.
Self is nothing but an aspect reflection of consciousness,
Het zelf is niets anders dan een aspectreflectie van bewustzijn,
you know, in a specific definition. >> So in other words, quit verbalizing or
je weet wel, in een specifieke definitie. >> Dus met andere woorden, stop met het verbaliseren of
thinking about enlightenment and start experiencing it.
nadenken over verlichting en beginnen het ervaren.
>> Well, you're trying to get off the thinkingness,
>> Nou, je probeert er vanaf te komen denkvermogen,
>> right? So, um, what you do is you rehearse it. You have to go back into
>> toch? Dus wat jij doet, ben jij repeteer het. Je moet er weer in
the whole narrative, >> right?
het hele verhaal, >> toch?
>> There's some new words in our vocabulary. Narrative is one of them.
>> Er staan een aantal nieuwe woorden in onze vocabulaire. Het verhaal is er één van.
And when we all grew up with the story of things, now it's a narrative. You
En toen we allemaal opgroeiden met het verhaal van dingen, nu is het een verhaal. Jij
know, it's more fashionable. And I like to stay fashionable.
Weet je, het is modieuzer. En ik blijf graag modieus.
Say with narrative. >> You want to be in the present.
Zeg met verhaal. >> Je wilt in het heden zijn.
>> I want to be I don't want any stories anymore. I just want the narrative.
>> Dat wil ik zijn. Ik wil geen verhalen meer. Ik wil gewoon het verhaal.
You hear it all the time. >> New new thing, you know, narrative.
Je hoort het de hele tijd. >> Nieuw nieuw ding, weet je, verhaal.
There's new words all the time that didn't exist when I grew up. There's
Er zijn steeds nieuwe woorden bestond niet toen ik opgroeide. Er is
another common one in politics called vetting. Well, he hasn't been vetted
een andere veel voorkomende in de politiek genaamd doorlichting. Nou, hij is niet doorgelicht
yet. Or wait till he gets vetted. I don't think it's even in the dictionary.
nog. Of wacht tot hij is doorgelicht. ik denk niet dat het zelfs in het woordenboek staat.
Is it vetted? I never heard of it. I lived 80 years without ever hearing the
Is het doorgelicht? Ik heb er nog nooit van gehoord. ik leefde 80 jaar zonder ooit de
word vetted. And suddenly it's everything has to be vetted and this
woord doorgelicht. En opeens is het zo alles moet worden doorgelicht en dit
candidate has to be vetted and wait till he gets vetted. Is that a real word?
kandidaat moet worden doorgelicht en wachten tot hij wordt gescreend. Is dat een echt woord?
That a real word? >> Yeah, it is. I see someone's shaking
Is dat een echt woord? >> Ja, dat is zo. Ik zie dat iemand trilt
their head out. Yeah. >> I don't know where it got invented.
hun hoofd naar buiten. Ja. >> Ik weet niet waar het uitgevonden is.
>> Do you think it's in the dictionary? >> Vested.
>> Denk je dat het in het woordenboek staat? >> Gevestigd.
>> Vetted. Yeah. >> Is it vetted or vested?
>> Gekeurd. Ja. >> Is het doorgelicht of verworven?
>> No. Vetted. Vetted. >> Vetted.
>> Nee. Doorgelicht. Doorgelicht. >> Gekeurd.
with a T.
met een T.
>> I don't know. I think it's a I think it's a neologism.
>> Ik weet het niet. Ik denk dat het een ik denk het is een neologisme.
>> I think it's a neologism with no intrinsic historic reality
>> Ik denk dat het een neologisme is zonder intrinsieke historische realiteit
vocabulary viewpoint. >> Well, you've come out with a few new
woordenschat oogpunt. >> Nou, je hebt er een paar nieuwe uitgebracht
words like hermeneutics. Epistemology.
woorden als hermeneutiek. Epistemologie.
>> The hermeneutics. >> Oh,
>> De hermeneutiek. >> O,
>> the hermeneutics of relativistic epistemology.
>> de hermeneutiek van het relativisme epistemologie.
Well, that's just normal English. >> Yeah. Anybody got a dictionary? Look
Nou, dat is gewoon normaal Engels. >> Ja. Heeft iemand een woordenboek? Kijk
that one up. >> Well, those are real words. Those are
die op. >> Nou, dat zijn echte woorden. Dat zijn
real words. Those are not neologisms like vetting.
echte woorden. Dat zijn geen neologismen zoals doorlichting.
>> I What's epistemology? >> It's in the dictionary.
>> I Wat is epistemologie? >> Het staat in het woordenboek.
>> Oh, it is. Okay. You got to get one of those big ones to look these up.
>> O, dat is zo. Oké. Je moet er een krijgen die groten om deze op te zoeken.
>> Vetting is in there. >> I don't know.
>> Doorlichting zit erin. >> Ik weet het niet.
>> I'm gonna take it up with my congressman with their vetting is
>> Ik ga het bespreken met mijn congreslid met hun doorlichting is
>> really the American way. It doesn't sound American to me.
>> echt op de Amerikaanse manier. Dat is niet het geval klinkt voor mij Amerikaans.
>> So, so getting back then, we live in the So, in order to
>> Dus, dus om terug te komen, we leven in de Dus om dat te doen
we have to train ourselves to live in the present,
we moeten onszelf trainen om in te leven het heden,
not in the past, not in the future, but just in the present.
niet in het verleden, niet in de toekomst, maar gewoon in het heden.
And if we do that then then are we living in the present of joy?
En als we dat doen, dan zijn we dat ook leven in het heden van vreugde?
>> Well, I wouldn't say it's the present of anything. It's just living in the
>> Nou, ik zou niet zeggen dat het het heden is van iets. Het is gewoon leven in de
present. And and living in the present is is free of negative emotion.
cadeau. En en leven in het heden Het is vrij van negatieve emoties.
>> Okay. >> Because you're not anticipating
>> Oké. >> Omdat je niet anticipeert
anything. You're not wanting to change anything.
iets. Je wilt niet veranderen iets.
You have to constantly let going to change things or make them different
Je moet voortdurend loslaten dingen veranderen of anders maken
and um decline the ego's offer of trying to juice it.
en eh, weiger het aanbod van het ego om het te proberen om er sap van te maken.
>> The ego is always trying to juice things. That's why we have such a
>> Het ego probeert altijd sap te krijgen dingen. Daarom hebben wij zo'n
struggle for moral superiority. You know, my folks were more wrong than
strijd om morele superioriteit. Weet je, mijn ouders hadden meer ongelijk dan...
yours. Oh yeah. Oh my mine were wrong. More wrong than yours. I mean
de jouwe. Oh ja. Oh mijn mijne hadden het mis. Nog fouter dan de jouwe. Ik bedoel
the fight for moral superiority. Who's the most wronged? Because if you're the
de strijd om morele superioriteit. Wie is het meest benadeeld? Want als jij de
most wrong, then you're the most justified in hatred.
het meest fout, dan ben jij het meest gerechtvaardigd in haat.
>> Yeah. Like mom likes you best. >> Uh
>> Ja. Alsof mama jou het leukst vindt. >> Eh
>> oh. >> You're mom's favorite.
>> o. >> Jij bent mama's favoriet.
>> Uh >> oh. Now you're in trouble.
>> Eh >> o. Nu zit je in de problemen.
>> See, that's what I mean. Those are the kind of things that, you know, your mind
>> Kijk, dat bedoel ik. Dat zijn de het soort dingen waar je verstand van heeft
wants to >> hang up on.
wil >> ophangen.
>> Yeah. >> Well, I you ask yourself, what is what
>> Ja. >> Nou, ik vraag je jezelf af, wat is wat
what what is the ego getting out of this?
waar komt het ego vandaan dit?
>> Okay. You know, it's a it's strictly narcissism
>> Oké. Weet je, het is strikt genomen narcisme
trying to juice the both the future and the past
proberen de toekomst en de toekomst te benutten het verleden
uh for excitement for one thing. >> Can you live without the excitement of
uh voor opwinding over één ding. >> Kun je leven zonder de opwinding van
anticipating the worst possible effect, you know? Yeah. And uh so what what is
anticiperend op het slechtst mogelijke effect, weet je? Ja. En eh, wat is dat dan
it that you have to let go of to to make the time mind stop?
het dat je moet loslaten om te maken de tijd dat de geest stopt?
Well, I recommend being bored with it.
Nou, Ik raad aan om je ermee te vervelen.
Well, after you hear this story so many times, you are kind of bored with it.
Nou, nadat je dit verhaal zo vaak hebt gehoord soms verveel je je er een beetje mee.
You know, >> I am bored with this with the
Weet je, >> Ik verveel me hiermee met de
>> I mean, even yourself, after you hear the same thing, it starts into the same
>> Ik bedoel, zelfs jezelf, nadat je het gehoord hebt hetzelfde, het begint op hetzelfde
bored thinking and all of a sudden, okay,
verveeld denken en plotseling, oké,
>> you ask yourself, now that I'm bored with it, why why am I rethinking it?
>> vraag je jezelf af, nu ik me verveel ermee, waarom denk ik er nog eens over na?
>> Right. >> Uhhuh.
>> Juist. >> Uhhh.
>> Okay. >> Well, that's an untrained mind.
>> Oké. >> Nou, dat is een ongetrainde geest.
Untrained. >> Okay. So a trained m mind can decide
Ongetraind. >> Oké. Dus een getrainde geest kan beslissen
uh to discontinue that >> right
euh om daarmee te stoppen >> gelijk
>> that particular line of inquiry or discussion
>> die specifieke onderzoekslijn of discussie
and but see what the mind then fears of nothingness
en kijk maar waar de geest dan bang voor is niets
and the pathway of negation you know hanging poe or the the pathway of
en het pad van ontkenning, weet je hangende poe of het pad van
negation is to let go of all contextual con conceptual thought to stop trying to
Ontkenning is het loslaten van al het contextuele con conceptueel denken om te stoppen met proberen
describe, think about, change, etc. Let go of all conceptual thought. If if you
beschrijven, nadenken, veranderen, etc. Laten laat al het conceptuele denken achterwege. Als als jij
do this, if you do the track that we're discussing,
Doe dit, als je het nummer doet dat we doen bespreken,
you will eventually end up at, you know, using the pathway of negation, not this,
Uiteindelijk kom je terecht bij, weet je, het pad van ontkenning gebruiken, niet dit,
not that, uh, you will end up at the void in which
niet dat, uh, je komt terecht in de leegte waarin
there is nothing and no one and nothing happening, which there is neither future
er is niets en niemand en niets gebeurt, waar geen toekomst in zit
or past nor anything imbecillic like now.
of verleden, noch iets imbecils zoals nu.
>> Um, >> the thought of now is itself is
>> Eh, >> de gedachte van nu is zichzelf is
imbecillic. But >> and this is popular at the moment. This
imbeciel. Maar >> en dit is momenteel populair. Dit
is kind of on the same subject. You today you were talking a little bit
gaat een beetje over hetzelfde onderwerp. Jij Vandaag was je een beetje aan het praten
about um people not having boundaries and I think
over ehm mensen die geen grenzen hebben, denk ik
it's that people don't have respect for one another as much as what they did.
Het is waar mensen geen respect voor hebben elkaar net zoveel als wat ze deden.
That's why the boundaries are no longer there.
Daarom zijn er geen grenzen meer daar.
>> I mean don't you feel feel that could be the problem is that we're not taught
>> Ik bedoel, heb je niet het gevoel dat dat zo zou kunnen zijn het probleem is dat het ons niet wordt geleerd
respect. Well, certainly in the modern media, uh, there is no such thing as
respect. Nou ja, zeker in het moderne media, er bestaat niet zoiets als
respect. >> I mean, blog bloggers get on there with
respect. >> Ik bedoel, blogbloggers gaan ermee door
the most insulting. I've I've never heard such incredible things as people
het meest beledigend. Ik heb ik nooit zulke ongelooflijke dingen gehoord als mensen
will put actually put on the web uh web uh system there. And not only that,
zal daadwerkelijk op het web worden gezet uh systeem daar. En niet alleen dat,
>> internet, >> whatever you call that, the blogger
>> internetten, >> hoe je dat ook noemt, de blogger
blogger world, they'll not only say something that is uh blasphemous and uh
bloggerwereld, zullen ze niet alleen zeggen iets dat uh godslasterlijk is en uh
>> incorrect >> and wrong, uh but they will even signify
>> onjuist >> en verkeerd, maar ze zullen het zelfs betekenen
who it is that that said it. >> I mean, I would change my name and move
wie het is die dat zei. >> Ik bedoel, ik zou mijn naam veranderen en verhuizen
to a different country having said such a thing. And uh they thrive on it. Mhm.
naar een ander land dat dit heeft gezegd een ding. En uh, ze gedijen ervan. Mhm.
>> So, we have a culture in which people become famous and rich
>> We hebben dus een cultuur waarin mensen beroemd en rijk worden
through hatred. There's big-time websites that get cited
door haat. Er zijn grote websites die worden geciteerd
all the time. >> So, how do we change that?
de hele tijd. >> Hoe kunnen we dat veranderen?
>> Oh, I don't want to change it. >> Well, how do we discourage that? Do we
>> Oh, ik wil het niet veranderen. >> Wel, hoe kunnen we dat ontmoedigen? Doen wij
um I mean, how do you discourage that action?
Ehm, ik bedoel, hoe ontmoedig je dat actie?
>> I don't want to discourage it. >> Because to discourage it, you become
>> Ik wil het niet ontmoedigen. >> Omdat je het ontmoedigt
involved with it. >> Well, yeah. And I don't want to become
erbij betrokken. >> Nou ja. En dat wil ik niet worden
involved with it. You know, how do you want to get rid of all the arsenic in
erbij betrokken. Weet je, hoe doe je dat? wil al het arsenicum kwijt
the soup? Well, you have to put your hands in the soup to get
de soep? Nou, je moet je handen in de soep te krijgen
>> So, you let all these people run a muck out here doing all this stuff over
>> Dus je liet al deze mensen hun gang gaan hier om al deze dingen te doen
>> whatever they're doing, they're doing. >> Yeah. That's not true and isn't going to
>> wat ze ook doen, ze doen het. >> Ja. Dat is niet waar en dat zal ook niet gebeuren
but it's affecting, you know, millions of people, but it's all like blah blah
maar het treft, weet je, miljoenen van mensen, maar het is allemaal bla-bla
blah blah blah blah blah. And it's half of it's not true and we're supposed to
bla bla bla bla bla. En het is de helft dat het niet waar is en dat zouden we wel moeten doen
let that go on. >> Uh well, that's what's called freedom.
laat dat doorgaan. >> Eh, dat is wat vrijheid heet.
I don't like it. >> Yeah.
Ik vind het niet leuk. >> Ja.
>> You see when you when you guarantee complete freedom, you're unccoring evil
>> Je ziet wanneer je wanneer garandeert volledige vrijheid, je ontmaskert het kwaad
and giving it permission and power. In a society in which over 50% of the people
en het toestemming en macht geven. In een samenleving waarin meer dan 50% van de mensen bestaat
calibrate 200, what kind of a society are you going to create? If you get if
kalibreren 200, wat voor soort samenleving ga jij creëren? Als je als krijgt
you give equality to everybody and majority are below 200
je geeft gelijkheid aan iedereen en meerderheid ligt onder de 200
>> you will get a degradation of society. Yes.
>> je krijgt een degradatie van de samenleving. Ja.
>> Mhm. >> If it wasn't for the fact that the few
>> Mhm. >> Als het niet zo was dat de weinigen
people of very advanced consciousness support the consciousness of all of
mensen met een zeer geavanceerd bewustzijn ondersteunen het bewustzijn van iedereen
mankind, mankind would have destroyed himself centuries ago.
mensheid, de mensheid zou hebben vernietigd zichzelf eeuwen geleden.
If you left it up to the popular vote, if you know survival was up to the
Als je het aan de volksstemming overlaat, als je weet dat overleven aan de orde was
popular vote, we wouldn't last till next weekend.
volksstemming, we zouden het niet volhouden tot de volgende weekend.
>> But I'm of the I'm of the culture, I guess you would say that, you know, when
>> Maar ik ben van de ik ben van de cultuur, ik Ik denk dat je dat zou zeggen, weet je, wanneer
you see a a a wrong, >> you want to, you know, correct that
je ziet een een een fout, >> je wilt dat corrigeren
wrong. >> Yes.
fout. >> Ja.
>> So, it's kind of difficult to stand by and watch a wrong continue to the point
>> Het is dus nogal moeilijk om stand-by te blijven en kijk hoe een fout verder gaat naar het punt
where it's overtaking. What is your obligation? What is your What is the
waar het inhaalt. Wat is jouw verplichting? Wat is jouw Wat is de
obligation? >> What is your moral
verplichting? >> Wat is jouw moraal
>> ethical obligation? >> What is it
>> ethische verplichting? >> Wat is het
>> to call a spade a spade? >> Well, it's not popular to call a spade a
>> een schop een schop noemen? >> Nou, het is niet populair om een schoppen a te noemen
spade. Uh what's popular is lying about something. Calling a spade a spade means
spade. Wat populair is, is liegen iets. Een schop een schop noemen betekent
confronting a statement with objective reality.
een verklaring met een doelstelling confronteren realiteit.
>> Oh, so you call a spade a heart. >> No, you could call a spade a spade out
>> Oh, dus jij noemt een schop een hart. >> Nee, je zou een schop een schop kunnen noemen
of your love for mankind. Yes. >> Let's see. Should we vote for him as
van uw liefde voor de mensheid. Ja. >> Laten we eens kijken. Moeten we op hem stemmen als
president for life? You know what I mean?
Voorzitter voor het leven? Weet je wat ik gemeen?
>> All the dictators around Castro, all these all these people.
>> Alle dictators rond Castro, allemaal deze al deze mensen.
>> Well, at one time they get the allegiance of all the people because
>> Nou, op een gegeven moment krijgen ze de trouw van alle mensen omdat
they popularize some ism >> and ride ride to power on some kind of
ze populariseren een bepaald isme >> en rijden, rijden naar de stroom op een of andere manier
an ism. >> Usually it's a you know justified
een isme. >> Meestal is het een je weet wel gerechtvaardigd
resentment over the past. you know what happened
wrok over het verleden. je weet wat er is gebeurd
centuries ago or another some other part of the world and you juice you juice it
eeuwen geleden of een ander deel van de wereld en jij maakt er sap van
for justification. Yeah.
ter rechtvaardiging. Ja.
So that's what the ego does in order to survive. It creates issues and it
Dus dat is wat het ego doet om dat te bereiken overleven. Het creëert problemen en zo
thrives on issues. It loves it loves all the isms and it loves strife because
gedijt op vraagstukken. Het houdt van het houdt van iedereen het ism en het houdt van strijd omdat
that's where it gets its juice. Egotism.
daar haalt het zijn sap uit. Egoïsme.
Yeah. And the narcissism uh keeps the mind active because the
Ja. En het narcisme uh houdt de geest actief omdat de
average person dreads the void. The average person dreads they think it's
de gemiddelde mens is bang voor de leegte. De De gemiddelde persoon is bang dat ze denken dat dit zo is
like death. Uh dreads the mind stopping. >> And then what they think if the mind
zoals de dood. Uh, ik ben bang dat de geest stopt. >> En wat ze dan denken als de geest
stops and then what? So it brings up survival. Brings up survival. So they
stopt en wat dan? Het brengt dus naar voren overleven. Brengt overleving naar voren. Dus zij
keep thinking and regretting living in the past and the future in order to
blijf denken en heb er spijt van dat je erin woont het verleden en de toekomst om dat te doen
assure their own survival of their own uh mind and egotism without something to
hun eigen voortbestaan verzekeren uh geest en egoïsme zonder iets
think about the mind would go silent. Most people would dread that. Most
denk erover na dat de geest stil zou worden. De meeste mensen zouden daar bang voor zijn. Meest
people consider the >> okay that makes
mensen beschouwen de >> oké dat maakt
>> the void uh you know if you do keep doing the pathway of negation
>> de leegte, uh, je weet het als je het behoudt het pad van ontkenning bewandelen
not this not that letting go desiring letting letting going attraction and
niet dit, niet dat loslaten van verlangen loslaten, loslaten, aantrekkingskracht en
letting go aversion. If you let go attraction and aversion, eventually the
afkeer loslaten. Als je loslaat aantrekking en afkeer, uiteindelijk de
mind will become silent. And there you are in an infinite in an
de geest zal stil worden. En daar ben je in een oneindigheid in een
infinite state. Extremely impressive, extremely terrific.
oneindige staat. Zeer indrukwekkend, buitengewoon geweldig.
And you're sure that this is this is the ultimate state that the great gurus and
En je weet zeker dat dit het is ultieme staat dat de grote goeroes en
enlightened beings have described over the centuries.
verlichte wezens hebben beschreven de eeuwen.
And in this lifetime at age three, that was the state that prevailed
En in dit leven, op driejarige leeftijd, dat was de staat die de overhand had
that came in out of the absolute infinite nothingness
dat uit het absolute kwam oneindig niets
into existence. And it was a fantastic shock, out of the
tot bestaan. En het was een fantastische schok, uit de
infinite silence of infinite nothingness where I should
oneindige stilte van oneindig niets waar ik dat zou moeten doen
have stayed to tell you the truth. >> No, we need you here.
ben gebleven om je de waarheid te vertellen. >> Nee, we hebben je hier nodig.
came the stunning awareness of existence. I was age three
kwam het verbluffende bewustzijn van bestaan. Ik was drie jaar oud
and this little body is sitting in this little wagon on a sunny day
en dit kleine lijfje zit hierin kleine wagen op een zonnige dag
and all of a sudden out of the infinite silence of nothingness
en plotseling uit het oneindige stilte van het niets
there was the stunning awareness of existence
daar was het verbluffende bewustzijn van bestaan
and the confrontation with the conundrum is the infinite truth, the infinite
en de confrontatie met het raadsel is de oneindige waarheid, het oneindige
state, nothingness or allness. And it took some 30 years in this
staat, niets of alheid. En het duurde zo'n 30 jaar
lifetime to transcend that. Is it nothingness or allness?
leven om dat te overstijgen. Is het niets of alheid?
That's level 850 of nothingness versus allness. So what happens in trying to
Dat is niveau 850 van niets versus alheid. Dus wat gebeurt er als je het probeert
live in the now is one get one gets stuck with the talkingness of the mind
leven in het nu is één krijgen, één krijgen vastgelopen met de spraak van de geest
which needs to do that in order to survive. And if you try to stop it, up
die dat moet doen om dat te kunnen doen overleven. En als je het probeert te stoppen, omhoog
comes the fear of the void, of being nothing.
komt de angst voor de leegte, voor het zijn Niets.
And so how to handle the void? I mention it because that's what stops a lot of
En hoe ga je om met de leegte? Ik vermeld omdat dat veel tegenhoudt
people from going the whole way is they come to nothingness and their fear of
mensen die de hele weg gaan, zijn zij tot het niets komen en hun angst voor
nothingness. If I have no opinions, if I have no conversation, if there is no
niets. Als ik geen mening heb, als ik geen gesprek voeren, als dat er niet is
present or future or past, then I come to a infinite vacuum,
heden of toekomst of verleden, dan kom ik in een oneindig vacuüm,
an infinite nothingness and voidness, which you know the mind will then start
een oneindig niets en leegte, waarvan je weet dat de geest dan zal beginnen
up in order to survive, you know. >> But what you're talking about is a lot
om te overleven, weet je. >> Maar waar je het over hebt, is veel
of times family type anguish. Mhm. >> This member, the family did or said
vaak familie-achtige angst. Mhm. >> Dit lid heeft of zei de familie
that, this member. >> So, the family serves to keep things
dat, dit lid. >> Het gezin dient dus om dingen te behouden
stirred up. >> The purpose of your family is to prevent
opgeschrikt. >> Het doel van uw gezin is om te voorkomen
you from becoming enlightened by keeping you stirred up as the duty of all
je zult niet verlicht worden door te behouden jij bent in beweging gekomen als de plicht van iedereen
mothers, mother-in-laws, >> fathers, father-in-laws, sister-in-laws,
moeders, schoonmoeders, >> vaders, schoonvaders, schoonzusters,
and siblings is to keep you sufficiently stirred up that you won't become
en broers en zussen is om u voldoende te onderhouden opgewonden dat je dat niet zult worden
enlightened, which would leave them trailing behind.
verlicht, die hen zou verlaten achterop.
That's true. I mean, >> is that it?
Dat is waar. ik bedoel, >>is dat het?
>> Well, when you stop to think about it, that there is a lot, you know, to family
>> Nou, als je erover nadenkt, dat er veel is, weet je, in familie
and >> Yeah. keeps the pot stirred all the
en >> Ja. houdt de pot de hele tijd geroerd
time. >> Keeps the pot stirred.
tijd. >> Houdt de pot geroerd.
>> That's what mother-in-laws are for, isn't it?
>> Daar zijn schoonmoeders voor, nietwaar?
>> I don't know. I'm not one yet. Well, I'm just thinking of the old
>> Ik weet het niet. Ik ben er nog geen. Nou, ik denk alleen maar aan het oude
mother-in-law joke, you know. >> Yeah.
schoonmoedergrapje, weet je. >> Ja.
>> Standard, the stereotype of the mother-in-law. Uh,
>> Standaard, het stereotype van de schoonmoeder. Eh,
>> keeps the mind going. And did you see what she wore? You know,
>> houdt de geest gaande. En heb je het gezien? wat ze droeg? Weet je,
>> so there's a payoff of excitement >> and a feeling of aliveness. I don't want
>> dus er is een uitbetaling van opwinding >> en een gevoel van leven. Ik wil niet
to put, you know, thinking this down, >> right? there's a a feeling of aliveness
om neer te zetten, weet je, als je dit overdenkt, >> toch? er is een gevoel van levendheid
that you are aliveness through awareness.
waar je door leeft bewustzijn.
So it's it's an aspect of of being aware that you are awareness of your existence
Het is dus een aspect van bewust zijn dat je je bewust bent van je bestaan
by the virtue of the fact that you do enter into the social dialogue and we
op grond van het feit dat je dat doet gaan de sociale dialoog aan en wij
care about politics and we argue. Mhm. >> My my father I can remember at the
geven om politiek en we maken ruzie. Mhm. >> Mijn mijn vader kan ik me herinneren op de
dinner dinner dinner dinner dinner
diner diner diner diner diner
dinner dinner dinner table my father would rant and rave about politics and
diner diner diner tafel mijn vader zou tieren en enthousiast zijn over politiek en
my mother would sit there and say Ray Ray the children I'm bomb bomb moment
mijn moeder zat daar en zei Ray Straal de kinderen uit. Ik ben een bom-bom-moment
he's going on and he would get red in the face and his dinner would be getting
hij gaat door en hij zou rood worden het gezicht en zijn diner zouden krijgen
cold and he's going on about politics and the politicians and uh
koud en hij heeft het over politiek en de politici en uh
and then I was trying to remember Was he pro- Roosevelaf or anti-Russeld? I
en toen probeerde ik me te herinneren. Was hij dat? pro-Roosevelaf of anti-Russeld? ik
couldn't remember. After months and years of listening to
kon het me niet herinneren. Na maanden en jaren luisteren
him rant about the WPA and and socialism and the unions and
hij tekeer over de WPA en het socialisme en de vakbonden en
years every night at dinner and I could not remember if he's pro or pro or
jaar elke avond tijdens het avondeten en dat kon ik Ik weet niet meer of hij pro of pro is
against FDR. I remember I had to use the arm.
tegen FDR. Ik herinner me dat ik de arm moest gebruiken.
>> Yeah, he was against. Was he? >> Yeah. Here, let's use the arm. I have
>> Ja, hij was tegen. Was hij dat? >> Ja. Laten we hier de arm gebruiken. Ik heb
permission to ask about my dad. He was anti- FDR resist. Okay.
toestemming om naar mijn vader te vragen. Dat was hij anti-FDR-resist. Oké.
I remember the emotionality. I remember it getting red. My mother would say,
Ik herinner me de emotionaliteit. Ik herinner het me het wordt rood. Mijn moeder zou zeggen:
"Ray, Ray, your dinner's getting cold. The children, you know,
'Ray, Ray, je eten wordt koud. De kinderen, weet je,
FTR was the king of evil in this world." >> So, in the end, it doesn't really make
FTR was de koning van het kwaad in deze wereld." >> Dus uiteindelijk slaat het niet echt op
any difference. >> Well, that's what I'm saying.
enig verschil. >> Nou, dat is wat ik zeg.
>> It was the emotionality and the ranting. And I can't even remember whether it's
>> Het was de emotionaliteit en het tirades. En ik kan me niet eens herinneren of dat zo is
anti or pro, you know. See, I had to use the arm to
anti of pro, weet je. Kijk, ik moest gebruiken de arm aan
after all those years, you'd think you'd certainly know. Did he hate Roosevelt or
na al die jaren zou je dat wel denken weet het zeker. Haatte hij Roosevelt of...
think Roosevelt was the savior of society?
waarvan Roosevelt de redder was maatschappij?
>> So, >> and I couldn't remember which way it
>> Dus, >> en ik kon me niet herinneren welke kant het op ging
was. >> So, when you go to let go of this and
was. >> Dus als je dit loslaat en
make the mind go silent, then what we're doing is, you know, you you've talked
laat de geest stil worden, en dan wat we zijn doen is, weet je, je hebt gepraat
several times about the thought coming up like a wave. Yeah. And you know, you
meerdere keren over de gedachte die opkwam omhoog als een golf. Ja. En weet je, jij
know, the dog rover, >> the rover gets hit and you come up and
weet je, de hondenrover, >> de rover wordt geraakt en jij komt naar boven en
you come, >> it grows and grows and it grows. So what
jij komt, >> het groeit en groeit en het groeit. Dus wat
you do is you try and nip it in the bud >> before it even starts.
Wat je doet, is proberen het in de kiem te smoren >> voordat het überhaupt begint.
>> Yeah. >> In other words, the dog's thought comes
>> Ja. >> Met andere woorden: de gedachte van de hond komt
into your mind and you block it out. >> Yeah. It begins to come up. It's not
in je hoofd en je blokkeert het. >> Ja. Het begint op te komen. Dat is het niet
quite a dog yet, but it the longer you wait, it becomes a dog. Then it becomes
Nogal een hond, maar hoe langer je blijft Wacht, het wordt een hond. Dan wordt het
old rover and then it becomes how old Rover was run over and
oude rover en dan wordt het hoe oud Rover werd overreden en
>> so then you >> and a whole sad story. Yeah. So if you
>> dus jij dan >> en een heel triest verhaal. Ja. Dus als jij
drop that thought then another thought just pops in.
laat die gedachte vallen en dan nog een gedachte komt gewoon binnen.
>> Yep. >> Of something. And you drop that thought
>> Ja. >> Van iets. En je laat die gedachte vallen
too. Yeah. And then another thought comes in. You keep dropping those
te. Ja. En dan nog een gedachte komt binnen. Je laat ze steeds vallen
thoughts. >> Then then if you get a a divine
gedachten. >> Dan, als je een goddelijk krijgt
inspiration, you notice that the mind despite all this seeming talkingness,
inspiratie, dat merk je aan de geest ondanks al dit schijnbare gepraat,
the mind is actually silent all the time.
de geest is eigenlijk de hele tijd stil tijd.
>> Okay. >> Although you think your mind is talking
>> Oké. >> Hoewel je denkt dat je geest aan het praten is
and thinking, it actually isn't. >> Right?
en denken: dat is het eigenlijk niet. >> Toch?
>> The mind is actually doing nothing. the phenomena are being witnessed and
>> De geest doet eigenlijk niets. de verschijnselen worden waargenomen en
you're identifying with that and think that's thinking.
je identificeert je daarmee en denkt na dat is denken.
The only one who thinks that that's thinking is you.
De enige die denkt dat dat zo is denken ben jij.
>> Okay? the universe thinks it's >> so in other words you kind of go into
>> Oké? het universum denkt van wel >> dus met andere woorden, je gaat er een beetje op in
you kind of go into a contemplation only it's like all this stuff is
je gaat als het ware in contemplatie alleen het is zoals al dit spul is
happening over here but you are actually contemplating
gebeurt hier, maar dat is eigenlijk zo nadenkend
uh the peacefulness here or the >> you're not even contemplating it you're
uh de rust hier of de >> je denkt er niet eens over na
being it >> right
het zijn >> gelijk
>> as we're talking right now my mind is silent
>> terwijl we nu aan het praten zijn, is mijn geest stil
>> the talkingness is doing its talkingness autonomously ly I myself
>> de praat doet zijn praat autonoom ikzelf
am not thinking nor am I even interested in thinking I mean thinking this would
Ik denk niet na en ben zelfs niet geïnteresseerd met denken bedoel ik dat ik denk dat dit zou gebeuren
disrupt the inner peace and silence so the talkingness is going on in the
zo de innerlijke rust en stilte verstoren er wordt gepraat in de
surface of the mind is not really who I am or where I'm at who I am and where
Het oppervlak van de geest is niet echt wie ik ben ben of waar ik ben, wie ik ben en waar
I'm at isn't even here and now tell you the truth it has no place in time or
Ik ben hier niet eens en vertel het je nu de waarheid heeft geen plaats in de tijd of
position or place >> so would you say that you're kind of
positie of plaats >> dus zou je zeggen dat je een beetje bent?
training your mind to do this And that's why you always tell us to go contemplate
je geest trainen om dit te doen. En dat is het waarom je ons altijd zegt dat we moeten gaan nadenken
um you know when you say you know say you have a verse
Ehm, je weet het als je zegt dat je het weet je hebt een vers
>> say you're doing the course of miracles and you have that verse for that day
>> zeggen dat je de cursus der wonderen doet en je hebt dat vers voor die dag
>> and you're supposed to repeat that verse over and over again. So in other words
>> en je wordt verondersteld dat vers te herhalen keer op keer. Dus met andere woorden
while you're doing >> reading or doing something else that
terwijl je bezig bent >> lezen of iets anders doen
verse is in the back of your mind and you keep re repeating that over and
vers zit in je achterhoofd en je blijft dat keer op keer herhalen
over. So you're actually trying to divide your mind into two different
over. Dus dat probeer je eigenlijk verdeel je geest in twee verschillende
sections so that you can go into that high spiritual place. It's like there's
secties, zodat u daarop kunt ingaan hoge spirituele plek. Het is alsof er
different layers to the mind. The most superficial and then the deeper. So what
verschillende lagen van de geest. Het meest oppervlakkig en dan de diepere. Dus wat
happens is you let go of the amusement because what the mind is doing is
wat er gebeurt is dat je het amusement loslaat want wat de geest doet, is
amusing you all the time. It's amusing. That's all it's doing. Gives you this
ik vermaak je de hele tijd. Het is grappig. Dat is alles wat het doet. Geeft je dit
long sad narrative or this scary one about the future and all. Uh but with
lang droevig verhaal of dit enge verhaal over de toekomst en zo. Eh, maar met
within all the talkingness uh is an infinite silence.
binnen al het gepraat uh is een oneindige stilte.
I said people are afraid of that silence for fear they will fall into the void.
Ik zei dat mensen bang zijn voor die stilte uit angst dat ze in de leegte zullen vallen.
Uh they're afraid they will fall into the void and therefore
Uh, ze zijn bang dat ze erin zullen vallen de leegte en daarom
they try to cover it up. The easiest way I describe it from a practical clinical
ze proberen het te verdoezelen. De gemakkelijkste manier Ik beschrijf het vanuit een praktische kliniek
viewpoint is that the silence is not in sequence
gezichtspunt is dat de stilte niet opeenvolgend is
with the mind. It's underneath the mind >> underneath all the talkingness like this
met de geest. Het zit onder de geest >> onder al dat gepraat
mind is talking right now. Well, that's just the service of the mind. The real
de geest is nu aan het praten. Nou ja, dat is het slechts de dienst van de geest. De echte
mind, the closer to that which I am is silent. It's not even interested in
geest, hoe dichter bij dat wat ik ben is stil. Het is niet eens geïnteresseerd
what's being going what's going on. It's just in a state of beingness and isness.
wat is er aan de hand, wat is er aan de hand. Het is gewoon in een staat van zijn en zijn.
So, it's like a big empty coliseum, you know, and then over in the corner of
Het is dus net een groot leeg Colosseum, weet je, en dan daar in de hoek van
the coliseum, there's some talking going on, but I'm aware that the coliseum is
het Colosseum, er wordt wat gepraat aan, maar ik ben me ervan bewust dat het Colosseum dat is
99.9% empty. There's nothing going on. So underneath the waves on the surface
99,9% leeg. Er is niets aan de hand. Dus onder de golven aan de oppervlakte
of the sea the sea goes down thousands of feet of
van de zee de zee daalt duizenden meters diep
silence and this talkingness is only on the surface.
stilte en dit praten is alleen maar aan het oppervlak.
So is even as I'm talking now even as you're listening now it's only the top
Dus is zelfs zoals ik nu praat, zelfs als je luistert nu, het is alleen de top
surface of your mind that's listening or thinking about it. I wouldn't bother
oppervlak van je geest dat luistert of erover nadenken. Ik zou er geen moeite mee hebben
listening or thinking to it about it at all. Underneath the listeningness
luisteren of erover nadenken op alle. Onder het luisteren
is an infinite silence. And if I ask the real you what was just said, you won't
is een oneindige stilte. En als ik het vraag aan de Als je echt bent wat er net is gezegd, zul je dat niet doen
even know. Your real self doesn't know what was just said. It's not even
weet het zelfs. Je echte zelf weet het niet wat er net werd gezegd. Het is niet eens
involved. If I say to the sea 600 ft down, what what just happened on the
betrokken. Als ik tegen de zee zeg: 180 meter naar beneden, wat er net is gebeurd op de
surface? The sea says, what do I care? Where I live, there aren't any waves.
oppervlak? De zee zegt: wat kan het mij schelen? Waar ik woon, zijn er geen golven.
There aren't any birds flying around. >> Okay,
Er vliegen geen vogels rond. >> Oké,
>> there isn't any garbage floating on the ocean.
>> er drijft geen afval op oceaan.
What I am is still and undisturbed by all that. That's all superficial that
Wat ik ben is nog steeds en ongestoord door dat allemaal. Dat is allemaal oppervlakkig
comes and goes with the wind and the tides.
komt en gaat met de wind en de getijden.
So this type of meditation this contemplation the type of meditation you
Dus dit soort meditatie is dit overpeinzing het soort meditatie dat je doet
can do even though you're proceeding in daily events and you once
kunt doen, ook al ben je dat wel doorgaan met dagelijkse gebeurtenissen en jij een keer
you train yourself that you can you always have this under the surface and
je traint jezelf dat je het kunt zorg dat je dit altijd onder de oppervlakte hebt en
you can do this even though you're uh fixing dinner or washing
Je kunt dit doen, ook al ben je eh eten klaarmaken of wassen
>> right. So this mind this mind what the world would call this mind is doing it
>> gelijk. Dus deze geest deze geest wat de de wereld zou deze geest noemen, doet het
right now as we talk as we talk that which I really am is
nu we praten terwijl we praten, is dat wat ik werkelijk ben
undisturbed unimpeded
ongestoord ongehinderd
>> so would you say >> not linear because talkingness is linear
>> dat zou je zeggen >> niet lineair omdat praten lineair is
right you're conceptualizing >> and that which we are is nonlinear so
goed, je bent aan het conceptualiseren >> en dat wat wij zijn is dus niet-lineair
your infinite self isn't really listening either it's only
je oneindige zelf luistert ook niet echt, het is alleen maar
our talkingness that's listening to each other.
onze spraak die naar iedereen luistert ander.
>> So that you're you're you're saying that the spirit itself, even though all these
>> Dus dat zeg je de geest zelf, ondanks al deze dingen
things happen in your life, all these, you know, different events happen in
Er gebeuren dingen in je leven, dit alles, Weet je, er gebeuren verschillende gebeurtenissen in
your life, the true spirit, it really doesn't affect it like the like the
je leven, de ware geest, het is echt heeft er geen invloed op, zoals het
deepness of the sea, your spirit isn't affected by all this that's going on up
diepte van de zee, jouw geest niet beïnvloed door alles wat er gaande is
here in the top. >> It only gets messed up when it
hier bovenaan. >> Het wordt pas een puinhoop als het zover is
identifies with that and thinks that who it who it is.
identificeert zich daarmee en denkt dat wie het wie het is.
when it thinks that I am the the I >> with the the small self
wanneer het denkt dat ik de ik ben >> met het kleine zelf
>> if it identifies with it then it gets messed up but the real self with a
>> als het zich ermee identificeert, dan wordt het verprutst, maar het echte zelf met een
capital S is not even interested in such things
hoofdletter S is daar niet eens in geïnteresseerd dingen
there's nothing to nothing to gain and nothing to lose so why would it be
er is niets tot niets te winnen en niets te verliezen dus waarom zou het zijn
interested it doesn't need novelty
geïnteresseerd het heeft geen nieuwigheid nodig
>> because only the ego wants constant amusement
>> omdat alleen het ego constant wil amusement
So you see how the mind fears >> uh boredom.
Zo zie je hoe de geest vreest >> eh verveling.
I think it hates worse is that nothing is happening.
Ik denk dat het erger is dat er niets is gebeurt.
Somebody says what's happening and I say well to tell you the truth uh absolutely
Iemand zegt wat er gebeurt en ik zeg Nou om je de waarheid te zeggen, absoluut
nothing. >> Okay, that explains it. I I was always
Niets. >> Oké, dat verklaart het. Ik was altijd
wondering what how that you know. So actually it's it's like 27 You teach
Ik vraag me af hoe je dat weet. Dus eigenlijk is het zoiets als 27 Je geeft les
yourself to have this contemplation, but that you can still deal with every day
jezelf om deze contemplatie te hebben, maar waar je nog elke dag mee te maken kunt krijgen
here on the surface, but yet you constantly are contemplating
hier aan de oppervlakte, maar toch jij voortdurend aan het nadenken zijn
the spiritual self underneath that >> to the identification with the infinite
het spirituele zelf daaronder >> naar de identificatie met het oneindige
reality >> underneath the mind and thinkingness and
realiteit >> onder de geest en het denkvermogen en
the personality and all >> to not lose sight of that. To not lose
de persoonlijkheid en zo >> om dat niet uit het oog te verliezen. Om niet te verliezen
sight of that. >> Wow. I learned something.
zicht daarop. >> Wauw. Ik heb iets geleerd.
Congratulations. >> No, I don't want your peace of mind
Gefeliciteerd. >> Nee, ik wil je gemoedsrust niet
disturbed. >> Okay.
verstoord. >> Oké.
>> I don't want anybody's peace of mind disturbed.
>> Ik wil niemands gemoedsrust verstoord.
>> Well, it isn't. It's just that we're allowing all the external stuff to try
>> Nou, dat is het niet. Het is gewoon dat we dat zijn waardoor alle externe dingen kunnen proberen
and, you know, we're trying to filter it all out.
en weet je, we proberen het te filteren allemaal uit.
>> All right. So, freedom comes with the realization that you don't have to. The
>> Oké. Vrijheid komt dus met de realization that you don't have to. De
average person thinks, well, I have to be upset about what my mother said or my
average person thinks, well, I have to be upset about what my mother said or my
mother-in-law said, what the government said, or some politician said.
mother-in-law said, what the government said, or some politician said.
>> You know, it's like you're obligated. >> Mhm.
>> You know, it's like you're obligated. >> Mhm.
>> And you could release yourself from that presumptive obligation.
>> And you could release yourself from that vermoedelijke verplichting.
I asked anybody, have you ever taken a vow to stay uh you know to serve the
I asked anybody, have you ever taken a vow to stay uh you know to serve the
ego, to be its servant? No.
ego, om zijn dienaar te zijn? Nee.
Well, people adhere to it as though it was a vow and that their life depended
Well, people adhere to it as though it was a vow and that their life depended
on it. You know, >> it's possible to turn off the TV and
erop. Weet je, >> it's possible to turn off the TV and
still survive. >> Yeah, but then I might be bored. Oh god,
nog steeds overleven. >> Yeah, but then I might be bored. Oh god,
then I might be bored. You can see that the mind is instantly going to say,
dan verveel ik me misschien. Dat kun je zien the mind is instantly going to say,
"Yeah, but then I'll be bored." Boredom is the way is is the the way the
"Yeah, but then I'll be bored." Boredom is the way is is the the way the
ego looks at nothingness as boredom.
ego kijkt naar het niets als verveling.
Well, even when you watch TV, a lot of times you say, "Oh, I want to just turn
Well, even when you watch TV, a lot of times you say, "Oh, I want to just turn
on the TV and just veg, you know, and all this stuff is playing
op de tv en gewoon vegetarisch, you know, and all this stuff is playing
on the TV like this and you and I think if you even asked me what program it
on the TV like this and you and I think if you even asked me what program it
was, I couldn't tell you because I'm not it's just like mindless
was, I couldn't tell you because I'm not het is net als gedachteloos
chatter in the background sometimes." Ice Ice Road Truckers. What's
chatter in the background sometimes." IJs-ijswegvrachtwagens. Wat is
>> Dave loves Ice Road Truckers. >> You don't have to think at all.
>> Dave loves Ice Road Truckers. >> You don't have to think at all.
And these big burly guys just do their big burly Alaska thing. Cook everything.
And these big burly guys just do their groot potig Alaska-ding. Kook alles.
And you can watch the same program over and over again and never be bored. I
And you can watch the same program over and over again and never be bored. ik
don't know what it is about Ice Roads Trucker.
don't know what it is about Ice Roads Vrachtwagenchauffeur.
I've seen some of the same episodes five, six times and I'm never bored with
I've seen some of the same episodes five, six times and I'm never bored with
it. Alex comes on and he's all muscles and
Het. Alex comes on and he's all muscles and
tattoos >> and he's very religious, very Catholic.
tatoeages >> and he's very religious, very Catholic.
>> I like Alex. He's a >> and
>> Ik vind Alex leuk. Hij is een >> en
then the the priest blesses Alex. >> Yeah.
then the the priest blesses Alex. >> Ja.
>> Because he's got a whole family and kids.
>> Because he's got a whole family and kinderen.
>> He's a good Catholic. >> Yeah. Very big Catholic. And he's makes
>> Hij is een goede katholiek. >> Ja. Zeer grote katholiek. En hij maakt
no bones about it. So if you love him, you love his his Catholicism, too.
geen botten erover. Dus als je van hem houdt, you love his his Catholicism, too.
>> And then you got the bear, which is like a big burly guy that's like beep
>> And then you got the bear, which is like a big burly guy that's like beep
beep as he's talking.
piep terwijl hij praat.
They're beeping them out. >> Yeah. Their language, the truck drivers
They're beeping them out. >> Ja. Their language, the truck drivers
are so full of >> truck drivers,
zijn er zo vol van >> vrachtwagenchauffeurs,
>> expletives that it's kind of like every other word's bleeped out, you know.
>> expletives that it's kind of like every other word's bleeped out, you know.
Like in the service, you know, when you pass the you know what coffee,
Like in the service, you know, when you pass the you know what coffee,
>> there isn't any coffee. There's just effing coffee. You
>> there isn't any coffee. Er is gewoon koffie uitschenken. Jij
and the effing bread and the effing butter and
and the effing bread and the effing boter en
it's just part of the lingo of that that kind of macho world, you know.
it's just part of the lingo of that that kind of macho world, you know.
>> Yeah, >> that's just part of the lingo. So um so
>> Ja, >> that's just part of the lingo. Dus eh
now that we know how to contemplate and we know how to
now that we know how to contemplate and wij weten hoe
channel our mind in different directions and um
channel our mind in different directions en eh
we've discussed um what else you want to discuss?
we've discussed um what else you want to bespreken?
>> Oh nothingness. >> Nothingness. Okay.
>> Oh niets. >> Niets. Oké.
>> I've just completed my my dissertation on nothingness.
>> I've just completed my my dissertation op het niets.
>> Yeah. >> I just did it.
>> Ja. >> Ik heb het gewoon gedaan.
Well, we did, you know, we've done this dialogue before and we did it on prayer
Well, we did, you know, we've done this dialogue before and we did it on prayer
and we did it on guilt. >> Yeah.
en we deden het uit schuldgevoel. >> Ja.
>> You know, and we've done it on this and so I was trying to think of something
>> You know, and we've done it on this and so I was trying to think of something
else. Is there anything else that anyone would like to us to dialogue on?
anders. Is there anything else that anyone would like to us to dialogue on?
>> Um, the question is, do you have to go to the void or do you can you skip over
>> Um, the question is, do you have to go to the void or do you can you skip over
the void? You can't step over it because there's nothing to step over because
de leegte? You can't step over it because there's nothing to step over because
it's void and there's nobody to step over.
het is ongeldig and there's nobody to step over.
>> So then you have to go there, right? >> It's a state of the pathway of negation
>> So then you have to go there, right? >> It's a state of the pathway of negation
takes you there >> in which there is no one there, nothing
brengt je daarheen >> in which there is no one there, nothing
to observe, nothing happening and neither it's neither formed nor
to observe, nothing happening and neither it's neither formed nor
formless. And
vormloos. En
the the average person who gets there considers it a state of enlightenment.
the the average person who gets there considers it a state of enlightenment.
They think this is the state because it seems so much like what they have heard
They think this is the state because it seems so much like what they have heard
or read about it or believed about it that this must be the state of
or read about it or believed about it that this must be the state of
enlightenment that the Buddha and all talk about.
enlightenment that the Buddha and all over praten.
The only way there was the knowingness that that was
De enige manier there was the knowingness that that was
not the ultimate state was in the snowbank as a child as a yo as an
not the ultimate state was in the snowbank as a child as a yo as an
adolescent. It all all came to a silent stop
adolescent. It all all came to a silent stop
and everything was infinite beyond all time with no beginning and no ending.
and everything was infinite beyond all time with no beginning and no ending.
But it was irdiated with a love of such perfection and and dimension.
But it was irdiated with a love of such perfectie en dimensie.
It was the suffusion of infinite love. At that point, you have permission to
Het was de overstroming van oneindige liefde. Op dat moment heeft u daar toestemming voor
leave the body. And every time it's recurred,
verlaat het lichaam. En elke keer is het zo herhaald,
uh there is the temptation, the desire, and the permission to leave the body.
uh, er is de verleiding, het verlangen, en de toestemming om het lichaam te verlaten.
One time it happened right during a class. I was walking down the aisle.
Eén keer gebeurde het tijdens een klas. Ik liep door het gangpad.
>> It was at one of our lectures. >> The state came on
>> Het was tijdens een van onze lezingen. >> De staat kwam op
and u some little corner of the mind which I allowed to survive said now
en jij een klein hoekje van de geest die ik nu liet overleven
that's going to be ridiculous you collapsed and died right in front of
Dat zal belachelijk zijn, jij stortte in en stierf vlak voor zijn ogen
your whole audience what kind of a teacher would that be it
je hele publiek wat voor soort leraar zou dat zijn?
would start it would start gossip so
zou beginnen het zou zo beginnen met roddelen
for that reason I uh reowned the body but those states and come on. It
om die reden herkende ik het lichaam maar die staten en kom op. Het
happened another time when I cut the thumb off and uh and lay on the ground.
gebeurde een andere keer toen ik de Duim eraf en uh en ga op de grond liggen.
And that time I heard the the angels chant from the chorus of miracles.
En die keer hoorde ik de engelen gezang uit het koor van wonderen.
I was laying there and I had permission to leave and I heard like a a chanting
Ik lag daar en ik had toestemming om te vertrekken en ik hoorde als een gezang
choir in my in my mind angelic choir said I am not a body. I am a spirit. I
koor in mijn in mijn gedachten engelenkoor zei dat ik geen lichaam ben. Ik ben een geest. ik
am I am not a body. um to like reinforce that I had
ben ik geen lichaam. Ik hou van versterking die ik had
permission to leave the body. But I thought of those who still
toestemming om het lichaam te verlaten. Maar ik dacht aan degenen die nog steeds
depended on me and chose to breathe again. And each time it's happened when
was van mij afhankelijk en koos ervoor om te ademen opnieuw. En elke keer gebeurde het wanneer
it happened with my father, I couldn't let my father think that because of him
het gebeurde met mijn vader, ik kon het niet laat mijn vader dat vanwege hem denken
I had died in the snow in the ice. Uh so I breathed again. And one time I did it
Ik was gestorven in de sneeuw in het ijs. Eh dus Ik ademde weer. En één keer deed ik het
with a rebirther named Ren. And again the same state prevailed and I
met een wedergeboorte genaamd Ren. En opnieuw heerste dezelfde toestand en ik
thought I I will have to breathe again otherwise Ren will think that his first
dacht dat ik weer moest ademen anders zal Ren denken dat dit zijn eerste is
rebirthing client died because of him and he'd be stuck with guilt.
rebirthing-cliënt stierf door hem en hij zou met schuldgevoelens blijven zitten.
It would re sort of blow his rebirththing business doll to hell.
Het zou hem een klap geven wedergeboorte zakelijke pop naar de hel.
So each time uh I allowed the love to become an
Elke keer dus uh, ik liet toe dat de liefde een
attachment and I knew that I was allowing but I was allowing the love to
gehechtheid en ik wist dat ik dat was toestaand, maar ik stond de liefde toe
act in the form of a detachment. I wasn't obligated to do so. It was a
handelen in de vorm van een detachement. Ik was daartoe niet verplicht. Het was een
choice. >> So when you go into the to this
keuze. >> Dus als je hierop ingaat
>> if I was really enlightened I would have let them all feel guilty.
>> als ik echt verlicht was, zou ik dat gedaan hebben laat ze zich allemaal schuldig voelen.
>> Good breathing. Leave the world and guilt's your problem buddy.
>> Goede ademhaling. Verlaat de wereld en Schuldgevoel is jouw probleem vriend.
>> No, you still had work to do. You couldn't leave us yet. Okay. If you if
>> Nee, je had nog werk te doen. Jij kon ons nog niet verlaten. Oké. Als jij als
you go into the void. >> Yes.
je gaat de leegte in. >> Ja.
>> What pulls you out of that void? >> Nothing pulls you off.
>> Wat haalt jou uit die leegte? >> Niets houdt je tegen.
>> Love. Is it love that you feel when you're in
>> Liefde. Is het liefde die je voelt als je binnen bent?
that void that pulls you through to the other side? What pulls you through to
die leegte die je naar de andere kant? Waar je doorheen trekt
the other side? >> I I refuse it as the absolute state.
de andere kant? >> Ik weiger het als de absolute staat.
>> Right. >> I've gone into the void many times. I
>> Juist. >> Ik ben vaak de leegte ingegaan. ik
came into this lifetime in already in the void
kwam al in dit leven binnen de leegte
>> and then I had the experience of allness. See that's nothingness. The
>> en toen had ik de ervaring van alheid. Kijk, dat is niets. De
opposite of nothingness is allness. So nothingness is the void. But allness
Het tegenovergestelde van niets is alles. Dus het niets is de leegte. Maar alheid
includes the love of God, the radiance of which is overwhelmingly profound
omvat de liefde van God, de uitstraling waarvan het overweldigend diepgaand is
beyond time, beyond all limitation and forever. Therefore, the absence of
voorbij de tijd, voorbij alle beperkingen en voor altijd. Daarom is de afwezigheid van
that infinite divine love is why I refused the void the last time it came
die oneindige goddelijke liefde is de reden waarom ik weigerde de leegte de laatste keer dat deze kwam
up. >> Okay. So, when you're in the void, what
omhoog. >> Oké. Dus, als je in de leegte bent, wat dan?
do you look for to go to the other side? To go past the void,
Wil je naar de andere kant gaan? Om voorbij de leegte te gaan,
>> there isn't any you to to do. So, >> I know, but what do you look for? What's
>> je hoeft niets te doen. Dus, >> Dat weet ik, maar waar zoek je naar? Wat is
the trigger? What trigger word can you give us that Oh, yes. Well, I've already
de trigger? Welk triggerwoord kun je geef ons dat. O ja. Nou, dat heb ik al gedaan
there in the void. What do we, you know, do we pray? What do we do?
daar in de leegte. Wat doen wij, weet je, bidden wij? Wat doen we?
>> No, I've already told everybody how to get over 850. That is to refuse it. And
>> Nee, ik heb iedereen al verteld hoe dat moet krijg meer dan 850. Dat is om het te weigeren. En
instead of nothingness and voidness, >> chew for the allness of the love of God.
in plaats van niets en leegte, >> kauwen op de alheid van de liefde van God.
Allness. >> So God is not nothingness. God is
Alheid. >> God is dus niet het niets. God is
allness. >> So the void is there is no thing. See?
alheid. >> Dus de leegte is dat er niets is. Zien?
>> Yeah. And the phenomena occur of their own,
>> Ja. En de verschijnselen ontstaan vanzelf,
but they're all merely phenomenal. And you can see they're only phenomena. They
maar ze zijn allemaal slechts fenomenaal. En je kunt zien dat het slechts verschijnselen zijn. Zij
have they only have no other reality other than their their phenomenal
ze hebben alleen geen andere realiteit anders dan hun hun fenomenaal
transitory phenomenalness. You might say there is a higher reality.
voorbijgaande fenomenaliteit. Je zou kunnen zeggen er is een hogere realiteit.
The highest reality is one in which the love of God replaces all and is
De hoogste realiteit is er een waarin de liefde voor God vervangt alles en is
everything with no beginning and no end. And unless that state is there, it is
alles zonder begin en zonder einde. En tenzij die staat er is, is die er ook
not the ultimate state. Yep. So the infinite state is allness. Resist. Thank
niet de ultieme staat. Ja. Dus de oneindige staat is alheid. Weerstaan. Bedankt
you. >> Okay.
Jij. >> Oké.
>> The infinite state is allness in which the presence of God radiates forth.
>> De oneindige staat is het geheel waarin de aanwezigheid van God straalt uit.
The other thing that accompanies that radiance
Het andere dat daarmee gepaard gaat uitstraling
is like an unveiling of all that exists is divinity.
is als een onthulling van alles wat bestaat is goddelijkheid.
Now in that state the beauty of everything is overwhelmingly stunning.
Nu in die staat de schoonheid van alles is overweldigend prachtig.
This table this tablecloth even now is such and if I allow the state to
Deze tafel is dit tafelkleed zelfs nu en als ik de staat dat toesta
continue I won't be able to talk because the beauty of each thing is infinite and
ga door, ik kan niet praten omdat de schoonheid van elk ding is oneindig en
overwhelming. I mean even now this is really bothering
overweldigend. Ik bedoel, zelfs nu is dit echt vervelend
me. Unless I get it away I want to disappear into this.
mij. Tenzij ik het weg krijg, wil ik dat wel hierin verdwijnen.
Oh, baby. You see uh you have to guard yourself.
O, schat. Zie je, je moet jezelf beschermen.
You see when you start reaching these states like if I don't guard myself now
Je ziet wanneer je deze begint te bereiken zegt alsof ik mezelf nu niet bewaak
that which I am will dissolve into the infinite wonder and joy of you and we
dat wat ik ben zal oplossen in de oneindige verwondering en vreugde van jou en wij
suffuse into one and there's no two people to dialogue anymore. So I have to
overgieten in één en er zijn geen twee mensen niet meer in dialoog treden. Dus ik moet wel
maintain a meanness and a unice so that the
onderhouden een gemeenheid en een unice zodat de
dialogue can continue. >> I'll pinch you.
dialoog kan doorgaan. >> Ik knijp je.
>> Oh, I love it. Pinch me, baby. I
>> O, ik vind het geweldig. Knijp me, schatje. ik
know you want to kill that flower, don't you?
Als je weet dat je die bloem wilt doden, doe dat dan niet Jij?
This flower expresses the beauty of God. And you want to go and crumple it.
Deze bloem drukt de schoonheid van God uit. En jij wilt het gaan verkreukelen.
>> I'm gonna keep you here. >> Yes, that's right. In other words, you
>> Ik houd je hier. >> Ja, dat klopt. Met andere woorden: jij
you begin to notice as you're noticing that the mind is always pulling you
je begint het op te merken terwijl je het opmerkt dat de geest je altijd aan het trekken is
back, but you don't have to let it. >> Okay?
terug, maar je hoeft het niet te laten. >> Oké?
>> You don't have to let it. It's an option. See, because what you were
>> Je hoeft het niet te laten. Het is een optie. Kijk, omdat wat je was
saying before, you sound like you're bound by that,
zoals je al eerder zei, je klinkt alsof je dat bent daardoor gebonden,
>> right? >> No, you're not bound. Once you realize
>> toch? >> Nee, je bent niet gebonden. Zodra je het beseft
that you have the freedom to agree with it or refuse it,
waar je de vrijheid hebt om het mee eens te zijn het of weiger het,
you can either hang in with that uh you know it's it's form. So you can hanging
je kunt daar mee doorgaan, uh jij weet dat het zijn vorm is. Je kunt dus ophangen
in with form is valitional. You don't have to hang in with form.
in vorm is waardevol. Dat doe je niet moeten vasthouden aan de vorm.
>> There's no obligation uh to see things as separate uh or as
>> Er is geen verplichting uh om de dingen als afzonderlijk te zien, uh of als
with adjectives. That's not an obligation. But the mind sort of
met bijvoeglijke naamwoorden. Dat is geen verplichting. Maar de geest soort van
presumes that it's obliged obliged to u do all these things and act
gaat ervan uit dat het verplicht is verplicht om al deze dingen te doen en te handelen
in this way. It's not obliged. It's an option.
op deze manier. Het is niet verplicht. Het is een optie.
>> The mic can stop anytime. I just wanted to demonstrate you have an
>> De microfoon kan op elk moment stoppen. Ik wilde alleen maar aantonen dat je een
option. All right. >> Yeah.
optie. Oké. >> Ja.
The the first impulse is I have to make her happy and please her and do what she
De eerste impuls die ik moet geven haar blij en behaag haar en doe wat zij doet
wants me to do. At the same time, there's awareness that that's strictly
wil dat ik doe. Tegelijkertijd Er is een besef dat dit strikt genomen het geval is
an option. And uh
een optie. En eh
so in a way it's uh accepting that there is a greater freedom uh to putting up
dus in zekere zin accepteer je dat daar is een grotere vrijheid om op te zetten
with your mind than what you think. The average person sees themsel as the
met je geest dan wat je denkt. De De gemiddelde persoon ziet zichzelf als de
victim of the mind. >> No, you don't have to be the victim of
slachtoffer van de geest. >> Nee, je hoeft er geen slachtoffer van te zijn
the mind. You're only the victim of the mind because you agreeing you're
de geest. Jij bent slechts het slachtoffer van de omdat je het ermee eens bent dat je dat bent
agreeing to be so because you're getting enough juice out of it to make it
ermee akkoord gaan dat dit zo is, omdat je het krijgt genoeg sap eruit om het te maken
worthwhile. indignation and self-pity and moral grandiosity, you know, save
de moeite waard. verontwaardiging en zelfmedelijden en morele grootsheid, weet je, behalve
the world, etc. Save the seashells.
de wereld, enz. Bewaar de schelpen.
>> Well, you know, everybody wants to save the tree, you know, the tree huggers.
>> Nou, weet je, iedereen wil sparen de boom, je weet wel, de boomknuffelaars.
Let's save the tree. >> Oh, I know.
Laten we de boom redden. >> O, ik weet het.
>> You know, they want to they want to feel that they're um making a change.
>> Weet je, ze willen, ze willen voelen dat ze iets veranderen.
Well, well, >> you know, there's a certain self satisi
Nou, nou, >> weet je, er is een zekere zelftevredenheid
satisfaction from saying I helped make that change. You know, there in a And
voldoening door te zeggen dat ik heb geholpen die verandering. Weet je, daar in een En
there you go back to the ego. >> Yeah, you got it.
daar ga je terug naar het ego. >> Ja, je snapt het.
How did how did the woods survive for millions of years until you got here?
Hoe heeft het bos overleefd? Miljoenen jaren voordat je hier kwam?
Oh, wondrous tree hugger. Nobody loves the trees more than I do.
Oh, wonderbaarlijke boomknuffelaar. Niemand houdt meer van de bomen dan ik.
Well, and then they're saying, "Well, we we saved it from, you know, the
Nou, en dan zeggen ze: "Wel, wij we hebben het gered van, je weet wel, de
chainsaws that were going to cut >> Yeah. Yeah.
kettingzagen die gingen zagen >> Ja. Ja.
>> But if it weren't for the chainsaws, who would plant a new tree? Nobody. So, the
>> Maar als de kettingzagen er niet waren, wie dan wel? zou een nieuwe boom planten? Niemand. Dus de
only way little trees get reborn is somebody cuts them down, sells them."
De enige manier waarop kleine bomen herboren worden is dat iemand ze kapt en verkoopt."
My father used to run a tree farm. And uh he had a zillion trees in northern
Mijn vader had vroeger een boomkwekerij. En Hij had een ontelbaar aantal bomen in het noorden
Wisconsin. You know, 160 acres of trees. >> That's a lot of trees.
Wisconsin. Je weet wel, 160 hectare bomen. >> Dat zijn veel bomen.
>> Yeah. 160 acres. They all have to be dug up and planted and transplanted.
>> Ja. 160 hectare. Ze moeten allemaal worden gegraven op en geplant en getransplanteerd.
>> Mhm. >> And that kept the industry going because
>> Mhm. >> En dat hield de industrie draaiende omdat
they would cut down the trees, but then they also replanted a tree for every
ze zouden de bomen omhakken, maar dan ze hebben ook voor iedereen een boom geplant
tree that was cut down. >> So yeah, he ran a tree farm. And the
boom die werd omgehakt. >> Dus ja, hij runde een boomkwekerij. En de
reason for those trees was to replace the trees that had been cut down by the
reden voor die bomen was om te vervangen de bomen die waren gekapt door de
loggers. >> So we should all start tree farms if we
houthakkers. >> Dus als we dat willen, zouden we allemaal boomkwekerijen moeten beginnen
want to be a tree hugger, right? Oh, I think everybody should be growing a few
Wil je een bomenknuffelaar zijn, toch? O, ik Ik denk dat iedereen er een paar zou moeten kweken
trees someplace. >> Oh, I I agree.
bomen ergens. >> O, ik ben het ermee eens.
>> Grow them in your window. You know, you start with a little tree, you know, and
>> Laat ze groeien in je raam. Weet je, jij Begin met een kleine boom, weet je, en
then it gets to be a bigger and bigger and bigger tree and then you give it to
dan wordt het steeds groter en een grotere boom en dan geef je hem eraan
your mother-in-law for Mother's Day >> and then she has to deal with it, right?
je schoonmoeder voor Moederdag >> en dan moet ze er mee omgaan, toch?
>> Yeah. Get your cousin to dig it, play it for.
>> Ja. Laat je neef het graven en speel het voor.
>> All right. So, so then the the thing of interest in is to realize that you have
>> Oké. Dus dan gaat het erom Interesse in is beseffen dat je dat wel hebt
much greater freedom and option about being uh controlled by your allowing
veel grotere vrijheid en keuzemogelijkheden gecontroleerd worden door jouw toestemming
yourself to be dominated by your mentalizations.
jezelf te laten domineren door jouw mentalisaties.
Uh people allow themselves to be dominated by the egotism of
Mensen laten zichzelf dat zijn gedomineerd door het egoïsme van
mentalization and they don't realize they have the
mentaliseren en ze realiseren zich niet dat ze de
freedom to refuse it. You have the freedom to stop thinking.
vrijheid om dit te weigeren. Je hebt de vrijheid om te stoppen met denken.
And if I ask you what do you know, you honestly answer
En als ik je vraag wat weet jij, jij eerlijk antwoord
I don't actually know anything. The only way to really know a thing is
Ik weet eigenlijk niets. De enige manier om iets echt te weten is
to be it. So I don't know those doors over there.
om het te zijn. Dus ik ken die deuren daar niet.
I'd have to be them to know them because the only true knowingness is through
Ik zou hen moeten zijn om ze te kennen, omdat het enige ware weten is door
identity. As I've pointed out in my story about
identiteit. Zoals ik heb aangegeven in mijn verhaal over
the cat, only the cat knows what a cat is.
de kat, alleen de kat weet wat een kat is is.
>> Was that where the old wise tale walk a walk? You shouldn't criticize until you
>> Was dat waar het oude wijze verhaal liep? wandeling? Je moet geen kritiek leveren totdat je
walk in their shoes, you know. >> Oh,
in hun schoenen lopen, weet je. >> O,
>> is that where that old line comes? >> It certainly has an overlap with that,
>> is dat waar die oude regel komt? >> Het heeft daar zeker een overlap mee,
isn't it? Yes. >> Because, you know, they say never to
nietwaar? Ja. >> Omdat, weet je, ze zeggen dat nooit te doen
criticize another person until you've walked in their shoes.
bekritiseer een andere persoon totdat je dat gedaan hebt in hun schoenen liepen.
>> Walked a mile in their shoes. Yes. >> That's an old Native American saying.
>> Liep een mijl in hun schoenen. Ja. >> Dat is een oud Indiaans gezegde.
>> Yeah. >> Oh, I think it was moccasins.
>> Ja. >> Oh, ik denk dat het mocassins waren.
>> Moccasins. But, you know, it's like and it does
>> Mocassins. Maar weet je, het is zo en dat is zo
make sense, you know. >> So, uh maybe we should
logisch, weet je. >> Dus, misschien moeten we dat maar doen
should all have a little bit more compassion for the people that um are
zou allemaal een beetje meer moeten zijn medeleven met de mensen die eh zijn
around us. >> Yeah. Experiential instead of perceptual
om ons heen. >> Ja. Ervaringsgericht in plaats van perceptueel
>> to experience what that is, >> right? its reality instead of your
>> om te ervaren wat dat is, >> toch? zijn realiteit in plaats van de jouwe
perception of that reality. >> Right?
perceptie van die werkelijkheid. >> Toch?
>> So that's the difference between knowing essence and appearance.
>> Dus dat is het verschil tussen weten essentie en uitstraling.
So the real mind deals then with the reality of essence and it lets go of
Dus de echte geest houdt zich dan bezig met de realiteit van essentie en het laat los
appearance because it knows it's too sophisticated to fall for appearance
uiterlijk omdat het weet dat het ook zo is verfijnd om voor uiterlijk te vallen
anymore and it only focuses on essence.
meer en het richt zich alleen op de essentie.
So you can you can you know they can tell you what a wonderful medication
Dus je kunt, je kunt, je weet dat ze het kunnen zeg je wat een geweldig medicijn
this is. At the same time you see frankly it'll kill you. At the same time
dit is. Tegelijkertijd zie je het eerlijk gezegd zal het je vermoorden. Tegelijkertijd
they got the boy on the bicycle and the barking happy dog with his wagging tail
ze kregen de jongen op de fiets en de blaffende gelukkige hond met zijn kwispelende staart
which is the message. >> Mhm.
wat is de boodschap. >> Mhm.
>> Which is the message. If is taking this an innocent boy riding
>> Wat is de boodschap. Als dit een onschuldige jongen is die rijdt
his bicycle with a barking happy dog. No. Frankly it's lethal.
zijn fiets met een blaffende, vrolijke hond. Nee. Eerlijk gezegd is het dodelijk.
Of course, it's lethal and it could kill you and you could go blind and dumb and
Natuurlijk is het dodelijk en kan het dodelijk zijn jij en jij zouden blind en stom kunnen worden en...
all, but woof woof woof woof woof, >> you know, it's very difficult. We're
alles, behalve inslag, inslag, inslag, inslag, >> weet je, het is heel moeilijk. Wij zijn
bombarded by um ads and messages and >> messages on top of messages and um it's
gebombardeerd door um advertenties en berichten en >> berichten bovenop berichten en eh, zo is het
very difficult to discern a lot of times, you know, but when you present
heel moeilijk om veel te onderscheiden keer, weet je, maar wanneer je presenteert
it, then it's much easier to look at. I mean, ads every day say, "Oh, buy this.
dan is het veel gemakkelijker om naar te kijken. ik bedoel, advertenties zeggen elke dag: "Oh, koop dit.
It'll cure everything, you know, and then when you and then you tear it down,
Het zal alles genezen, weet je, en... dan wanneer jij en dan breek je het af,
it kind of goes, "Oh, it's uh
het gaat zo ongeveer: "Oh, het is eh
>> I could write much better ads. >> I get very frustrated with the
>> Ik zou veel betere advertenties kunnen schrijven. >> Ik raak erg gefrustreerd door de
advertising departments of many companies and they could get so much
reclameafdelingen van velen bedrijven en ze konden zoveel krijgen
more mileage for their money. I mean they really get uh
meer kilometers voor hun geld. Ik bedoel ze snappen het echt
you know >> they pay a huge amount of money and when
weet je >> ze betalen een enorme hoeveelheid geld en wanneer
you look how ineffective the ad is you know
je kijkt hoe ineffectief de advertentie voor jou is weet
>> the the world then you know we should wear all the troubles and the everything
>> de wereld, dan weet je dat we dat zouden moeten doen draag alle problemen en alles
like a like a light garment >> I think so
als een licht kledingstuk >> Ik denk het wel
>> and >> forget about all the pain and
>> en >> vergeet alle pijn en
>> suffering and know that we're not going to change that that it's been in the
>> lijden en weet dat we niet gaan om te veranderen dat het in de
world for many many years that's the karma of being a human
wereld voor vele vele jaren dat is de karma van het mens zijn
But we can make their suffering maybe easier and that's about the best we can
Maar we kunnen hun lijden misschien verzachten gemakkelijker en dat is ongeveer het beste wat we kunnen
do because of their karmic potential >> if we accept that that's the way the
doen vanwege hun karmisch potentieel >> als we accepteren dat het zo is
world is and that the world is actually fulfilling its purpose all the time.
de wereld is en dat de wereld werkelijk is altijd zijn doel vervullen.
I mean it it's evolutionary and uh the will of God is expressed as
Ik bedoel, het is evolutionair en uh de wil van God wordt uitgedrukt als
as the world and its evolution. So consciousness, humanness are all
als de wereld en haar evolutie. Dus bewustzijn en menselijkheid zijn alles
evolutionary and by being evolutionary they are the
evolutionair en omdat ze evolutionair zijn, zijn zij de
per perfect fulfillment of the will of God. Is not the will of God to be
per perfecte vervulling van de wil van God. Is dat niet de wil van God?
constantly learning, expanding, uh evolving.
voortdurend leren, uitbreiden, uh evolueert.
>> Uh that's the way we seem to be created. We
>> Eh zo lijken wij geschapen te zijn. Wij
don't stand still for two seconds. We're constantly moving, evolving.
sta geen twee seconden stil. Wij zijn voortdurend in beweging, evoluerend.
So when Mother Teresa I mean her you know she she went into the depths of
Dus als Moeder Teresa bedoel ik haar jou Weet dat ze de diepte in is gegaan
Kolkata and and saved well not saved uh she actually saved souls not lives
Kolkata en en goed gered, niet gered uh ze redde eigenlijk zielen, geen levens
>> is basically what she was doing. She was letting the soul cross over.
>> is eigenlijk wat ze aan het doen was. Dat was zij de ziel laten oversteken.
>> She was with her soul >> right because she worked among the very
>> Ze was met haar ziel >> juist omdat ze onder de zeer werkte
ill. Yeah, indeed. >> They had none nothing. I mean, there's
ziek. Ja, inderdaad. >> Ze hadden niets. Ik bedoel, er is
no >> people are totally gone and nobody to be
nee >> mensen zijn totaal verdwenen en er is niemand meer
with them. So, she was with them to the end.
met hen. Dus ze was met hen mee naar de einde.
>> So, they knew they were loved right to the very end.
>> Dus ze wisten dat ze geliefd waren helemaal tot het einde.
>> Mhm. >> So, in other words, don't you think she
>> Mhm. >> Dus, met andere woorden, denk je niet dat zij dat is
was I mean, she couldn't save the body, but she was saving the soul.
Bedoelde ik dat ze het lichaam niet kon redden? maar ze redde de ziel.
>> Yes. Because when you look within that being and connect with the reality of
>> Ja. Want als je daarbinnen kijkt zijn en verbinding maken met de realiteit van
their self, then they know that who they are is being recognized.
zichzelf, dan weten ze wie ze zijn zijn wordt erkend.
And I can remember patients brought up wrapped up in ropes and god knows what
En ik kan me herinneren dat patiënten grootgebracht werden gewikkeld in touwen en god weet wat
brought in and dumped on the floor of the hospital and the hopelessness and
binnengebracht en op de vloer gedumpt het ziekenhuis en de hopeloosheid en
the agony. And then when you looked at them,
de pijn. En toen je keek zij,
the a caringness arises from within. It's impersonal and the self of the
de zorgzaamheid komt van binnenuit. Het is onpersoonlijk en het zelf van de
other person rises because it's been acknowledged. Then you see that their
andere persoon staat op omdat het geweest is erkend. Dan zie je dat hun
suffering has stopped. >> The suffering stops in that instant. The
het lijden is gestopt. >> Het lijden stopt op dat moment. De
reality of who they are has been recognized.
werkelijkheid van wie ze zijn is geweest erkend.
>> So >> I'm sure that's what happened with her.
>> Dus >> Ik weet zeker dat dat met haar is gebeurd.
>> So even though she might not have saved the body, she actually saved the soul.
>> Dus ook al heeft ze misschien niet gered het lichaam, ze redde feitelijk de ziel.
>> Yes. That's all that matters. What happened to the body?
>> Ja. Dat is het enige dat telt. Wat is er met het lichaam gebeurd?
One job you can get on the other side is to be a greeter.
Eén baan die je aan de andere kant kunt krijgen, is een begroeter zijn.
It's a good job being a greeter. And as people come across,
Het is een goede baan om begroeter te zijn. En als mensen tegenkomen,
you reassure them that they are not dead, that they are where they are loved
je stelt ze gerust dat dat niet zo is dood, dat ze zijn waar ze geliefd zijn
and the you know like a greeter on the doorway of heaven. You know, you can
en de weet je als een begroeter op de deuropening van de hemel. Weet je, dat kan
have a sign says greeter. >> Are you going to be there for all of us?
Ik heb een bord, zegt greeter. >> Ben jij er voor ons allemaal?
>> Oh, yes. I've been a greeter. I've never been.
>> O ja. Ik ben een begroeter geweest. Ik heb nooit geweest.
I think being a greeter, well, I've been a greeter in this world, you know.
Ik denk dat ik als begroeter wel zo ben geweest een begroeter in deze wereld, weet je.
Anyway, being a greeter is very fulfilling because people die in agony
Hoe dan ook, een begroeter zijn is heel erg vervullend omdat mensen in doodsangst sterven
for Lauren, abandonment, all hope, uh self-hatred, I'm not worth saving, grief
voor Lauren, verlatenheid, alle hoop, uh zelfhaat, ik ben het niet waard om gered te worden, verdriet
over, why did I do this, and so most you a lot of people die in a state of agony,
over, waarom deed ik dit, en de meeste jij ook Veel mensen sterven in een staat van pijn,
but it's spiritual agony. Spiritual agony. And when you greet them with the
maar het is geestelijke pijn. Spiritueel nood. En als je ze begroet met de
truth of who they really are and the recognition of who they are, then the
waarheid over wie ze werkelijk zijn en de erkenning van wie ze zijn, dan de
joy springs forth again. So the soul that's so
de vreugde komt weer naar boven. De ziel dus dat is zo
depressed and hopeless and for, you know,
depressief en hopeloos en voor jou weet,
it it's recognized for its reality. >> So I think being a greeter on the other
het wordt erkend vanwege zijn realiteit. >> Dus ik denk dat ik aan de andere kant een begroeter ben
side is one of the greatest jobs you can get.
kant is een van de mooiste banen die je kunt hebben krijgen.
The car runs over them and they're screaming in pain and agony and oh God,
De auto rijdt over hen heen en ze zijn er schreeuwend van pijn en pijn en oh God,
how could you abandon me? And all of a sudden they fall into the arms of a
hoe kon je mij in de steek laten? En allemaal van een plotseling vallen ze in de armen van a
greeter angel who said, "Well, here you are. God bless you. You made it."
groeter engel die zei: "Nou, hier ben je zijn. God zegene je. Je hebt het gehaald."
I mean, it's such a relief, you know. >> It's time. Oops. I'm sorry. It's
Ik bedoel, het is zo'n opluchting, weet je. >> Het is tijd. Oeps. Het spijt me. Het is
>> You say you had us worried there for a second, but you made it to the cross.
>> Je zegt dat je ons daar een tijdje zorgen hebt gemaakt ten tweede, maar jij hebt het kruis gehaald.
>> All right. So, do we come to an end now? >> Yes. Um, we'll resume at about a quarter
>> Oké. Dus, zijn we nu aan een einde gekomen? >> Ja. Eh, we gaan rond kwart over weer verder
after 3, maybe a little later since we stopped a little later, but um, and then
na 3 uur, misschien iets later sinds wij stopte even later, maar eh, en toen
we'll resume with question and answers. Questions on this side of the room. Uh,
we gaan verder met vraag en antwoord. Vragen aan deze kant van de kamer. Eh,
the book signing will be on this side. >> I thought we were all done for the day.
de signeersessie zal aan deze kant plaatsvinden. >> Ik dacht dat we allemaal klaar waren voor vandaag.
We're not. >> Oh, good. I thought we were done and
Dat zijn we niet. >>O, goed. Ik dacht dat we klaar waren en
we're not done. Oh, good.
we zijn nog niet klaar. O, goed.